Maddy: One of the responsibilities you
have as a team leader is ensuring your
team is an equal and diverse environment.
Phillip: Respecting one another’s differences
and recognising that everyone deserves to be
treated with dignity and respect, is how an
organization keeps its culture vibrant and
healthy, as well meeting the legal requirements,
legislated by the Equality Act 2010.
It is against the law to treat people different
because of protected characteristics, so
as a team leader you need to be alert and
sensitive to this to protect your team.
Maddy: Protected characteristics
defined in law are:
• Age
• Gender reassignment
• Marital or civil partnership status
• Pregnancy or being on maternity leave
• Disability
• Race, colour, nationality,
or ethnic or national origin
• Religion or belief
• Sex
• Sexual orientation
Phillip: Your own organization will have
policies in place, based on the requirements
of the law, to protect equality and diversity,
so your first responsibility as a team leader
is to familiarize yourself with these polices.
But you shouldn’t think of equality
and diversity as just something you
should be reactively protecting.
As a team leader you should be
actively promoting it and trying to
expand the diversity of your team.
Maddy: So, let’s look at some of
the things you can do to promote
equality and diversity in your team:
Phillip: Take time to educate yourself
about different cultures, traditions, and
religions- The more you know about different
cultures, traditions, and religions, the
more you’ll be able to relate to members
of your team who come identify with them.
Think about doing small events to mark major
religious holidays, such as inviting members
of team who belong to a particular faith or
follow a specific tradition to give a short
presentation about the holiday if they’d like.
Maddy: Learn about different minorities
and the prejudices they face- This includes
LGBTQ+ people, people with disabilities,
and people from minority ethnic groups.
By taking time to learn about their history and
the discrimination they still face, you’ll be
more sensitive to their needs, especially if
they experience discrimination in the workplace.
Phillip: Look into diversity training schemes
for you and your team- There are lots of
different organisations, that offer training
to help you and your team, become more
aware of issues of equality and diversity.
Speak to your HR department to
see if there’s training available.
Some charities and advocacy groups
also offer partnership schemes,
that can improve your organisation’s
reputation as a diverse employer too.
Maddy: Be aware of unconscious biases-
Everyone has biases that affect
their beliefs and behaviours, even if
they’re not aware of them consciously.
It’s part of being human.
Learning to be more aware of your own biases, sets
a good example for your team and will help you
more effectively promote equality and diversity.
Phillip: Make your own stance clear- There
should be no room for doubt that you’re committed
to equality and diversity, and that you won’t
tolerate discriminatory actions or language.
You can do this by sending out messages to your
team affirming your commitment, perhaps tying it
into company values or using real-life examples.
Maddy: Talk to your team- This is one
of the most important things you can do.
Actively engage with your team so that
they have opportunities to talk to you,
about their concerns and their ideas.
This will again show your team that
you’re committed to promoting equality
and diversity, and it’ll help create
an atmosphere that’s more inclusive.
Your team will know that you’re approachable
and will feel more secure because of it.
Phillip: Organisations may have policies in
place regarding equality and diversity, but
it is down to you as a good leader, to ensure
that the needs of all those in your team,
are met in a respectful and responsive way.
It is also important that you realise,
that you have the potential to influence
others, through your own inclusive,
supportive, and respectful behaviour.